Finding aid of the Beowulf Thorne Papers
Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society
Beowulf Thorne Papers
1964-1999
2003-10
Thorne, Beowulf
4.0 linear feet 2 manuscript boxes, 2 cartons, 1 oversized box
Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender Historical Society San Francisco, California 94105
Beowulf Thorne (Jack Henry Foster) was a political activist on issues affecting PWAs (people with AIDS). He was one of the founders, with Tom Shearer, of the humor magazine, Diseased Pariah News (DPN). He used his skills as a writer, editor, and graphic artist on the magazine. The collection documents the operations, both commercial and artistic of DPN, as well as the work of Oakland's Condom Resource Center.
Access
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the Library by Daniel Bao on April 3, 2003.
Biography
Beowulf Thorne (born Jack Henry Foster) was born in San Diego on November 6, 1964. He attended the University of California, Santa Cruz. A political activist regarding issues affecting PWAs (People with AIDS), he was one of the founders, along with Tom Shearer, of the PWA humor magazine Diseased Pariah News (DPN). He used both his skills as a writer-editor and as a graphic artist in creating and publishing DPN. A total of eleven issues of Diseased Pariah News were published from 1990 to 1999.
Beowulf Thorne passed away from complications relating to AIDS on May 8, 1999, the second co-founder to pass away from AIDS (Tom Shearer passed away after the second issue of DPN was published). Thorne was memorialized in the final issue of DPN in an irreverently titled piece of which he would have approved: "Dang! Our Founder and Guiding Light Died."
Scope and Content of Collection
Few personal papers are included in this collection. It's primarily focus is on Thorne's experience as a person with AIDS (PWA). This collection mostly consists of the textual and graphic records of Diseased Pariah News. An additional series relates to Oakland's Condom Resource Center, headed by director Daniel Bao, who worked closely with DPN.
The series is organized into 5 series:
Series 1. Personal, 1964-1998
Series 2. Diseased Pariah News, 1990-1999
Series 3. Zines, 1990-1997
Series 4. Condom Resource Center, 1990-1998
Series 5. Photos/Artwork, 1989-1992
Series 5. Photos/Artwork, 1989-1992
Series 6. Objects, undated, 1990
Series 1. Personal, 1964-1998
This series consists of personal documents and other effects of Beowulf Thorne such as his passports, birth certificate, personal notes on his estate, and articles he wrote for POZ Magazine, a magazine for and about people living with HIV. There are also personal photographs in this series.
Series 2. Diseased Pariah News, 1990-1999
This series contains materials relating to the Thorne's magazine Diseased Pariah News. All eleven issues of the magazine are included as well as background materials and other items related to publishing the magazine such as drafts of articles, artwork and photographs. Also found in this series are reviews of the magazine and articles in other publications about DPN. Finally there are correspondence files containing letter to the editors requesting back issues, subscriptions, or expressing opinions about the magazine.
Series 3. Zines, 1990-1997
This series consists of other zines collected by Thorne. These publications had a similar irreverent approach to the AIDS crisis
Series 4. Condom Resource Center, 1990-1998
This series contains materials produced by the Condom Resource Center (CRC) in Oakland. Thorne worked very closely with this organization, helping create artwork and other content for their safe sex campaigns. Included in this series are examples of some of Thorne's artwork as well as photographs. There are also several publications put out by the CRC such as several versions of the Condom Educator's Guide.
Series 5. Photos/Artwork, 1989-1992
This series consists of the photographs and other artwork created by Beowulf Thorne. His skills as a photographer and an artist are illustrated by these items.
Series 6. Objects, undated, 1990
This series contains ephemera from Diseased Pariah News and other organizations.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
AIDS; San Francisco (Calif.); Persons With AIDS; AIDS Activists; Graphic Artists
Related Material
Diseased Pariah News(Periodical)
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Personal, 1964-1998; 11 folders
  This series consists of personal documents and other effects of Beowulf Thorne such as his passports, birth certificate, personal notes on his estate, and articles he wrote for POZ Magazine, a magazine for and about people living with HIV. There are also personal photographs in this series.
  - Birth Certificate, passport, vaccination record, 1964-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Notes on his estate (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Life insurance, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Article submitted to POZ on living with Lymphoma, 1988 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Notes for POZ article on Collateral Damage, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Notes for POZ article on Depression, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Notes for POZ article on Suicide, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Tienanmen week at Stanford, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Photos (Box-folder 1: 9-11)
    - "Steam" (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Personal (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - "A Certain Undisclosed Location in Long Beach" (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Series 2. Diseased Pariah News, 1990-1999; 45 folders
  Series Description
  This series contains materials relating to the Thorne's magazine Diseased Pariah News. All eleven issues of the magazine are included as well as background materials and other items related to publishing the magazine such as drafts of articles, artwork and photographs. Also found in this series are reviews of the magazine and articles in other publications about DPN. Finally there are correspondence files containing letter to the editors requesting back issues, subscriptions, or expressing opinions about the magazine.
  - Magazine (Box-folder 1: 12-22)
    - #1, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - #2, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - #3, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - #4, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - #5, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - #6, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - #7, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - #8, 1993 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - #9, 1994 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - #10, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - #11, 1999 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Articles (Box-folder 1: 23-30)
    - Notes for a story: "A Brief History of Malaysia" (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - The Art of Ralphing, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Submitted by Edward Zold, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - Annotated draft of articles for issue #11, 1989 (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - "Nutrition and PWAs from AIDS Patient Care", 1988 (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - Nutrition and Recipes, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - "Pseudo Intellectual Stuff from the Halls of Academe", 1996 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - "Vague Ideas for DPN", 1992 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - DPN Artwork (Box-folder 1: 31 - 2: 15)
    - DPN # 1, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - DPN # 2, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - DPN # 3, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 33)
    - DPN # 4, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 34)
    - DPN # 10, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 35)
    - Artwork by Kira (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - "Jesus Came to My House" (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - "History of Malaysia" (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Paper Merit Badges for DPN Buttons (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - DPN Photographs (Box-folder 2: 5-14)
    - DPN # 1, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - DPN # 2, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - DPN # 3, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - DPN # 4, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - DPN # 5, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - DPN # 6, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - DPN # 7, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - DPN # 8, 1993 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - DPN # 9, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - DPN # 10, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Press (Box-folder 2: 15-19)
    - Promotional Material (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Press Kit, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Articles, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Reviews, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Bay Guardian's Best of the Bay Award to DPN, 1996 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 2: 20-24)
    - Forms (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Postcards and Christmas Card Printed by DPN, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Letters from Fans, 1991-1999 (Box-folder 2: 22)
    - Letters from Prisoners Requesting Free Subscriptions, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Letters Requesting Back Issues, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 2: 24)
- Series 3. Zines, 1990-1997; 4 folders
  This series consists of other zines collected by Thorne. These publications had a similar irreverent approach to the AIDS crisis.
  - The Daily Plague #6 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Factsheet Five: Zine Reader, 1997 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - GAWK Newsletter (Gay Artists and Writers Kollective), #4-6, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - HardWear: The Art of Prevention, Hugh Rigby and Susan Leibtag, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Series 4. Condom Resource Center, 1990-1998; 14 folders
  This series contains materials produced by the Condom Resource Center (CRC) in Oakland. Thorne worked very closely with this organization, helping create artwork and other content for their safe sex campaigns. Included in this series are examples of some of Thorne's artwork as well as photographs. There are also several publications put out by the CRC such as several versions of the Condom Educator's Guide.
  - Condom Updates, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Corrected Draft and Layout of Condom Educator's Guide, ca. 1991 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Condom Educator's Guide, ca. 1991 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Condom Educator's Guide, Version Two, ca. 1994 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Artwork Related to Condom Educator's Guide, Version Two, ca. 1994 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Photos for Condom Educator's Guide, Version 2 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Official Condom Tester Catalog, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - National Condom Week Booklet, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - ondom Primer. # 1 and 2, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Party Packs, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Captain Condom's Original Party Pack Booklet, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Ephemera, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Artwork Related to CRC Poster and Handbook, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Artwork Related to CRC Organizer, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 15)
- Series 5. Photos/Artwork, 1989-1992; 24 folders
  This series consists of the photographs and other artwork created by Beowulf Thorne. His skills as a photographer and an artist are illustrate by these items.
  - Photos (Box-folder 3: 16-30)
    - My Vapid Youth (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Nerd Pictures (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - Use Your Head (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - Socks for Cocks (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - Biffy with Lube Bottles, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Cranky and Dusty Fellating Unseen Spirits, 1989 (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - Voyage of Dysfunctionality; Tommy Jo's Last Trip Home, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - Biffy Doing Rain Dance with Proper Prophylaxis (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Biffy's Publicity Pix: Nezz. Fezz,and Lezz, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - Greetings from Greater Slobovia (for GAWK #5), 1989 (Box-folder 3: 25)
    - Cranky, Humpy and Sleazy for DPN Xmas Card, 1991 (Box-folder 3: 26)
    - Use Your Head (Box-folder 3: 27)
    - Strange but True; Odd Bits of Tom Shearer (Box-folder 3: 28)
    - What's Wrong with This Picture? (unsolicited snapshots from fans) (Box-folder 3: 29)
    - Model Releases, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - Artwork (oversized box, 20" x 16" x 3.5") (Box-folder 4: 1-9)
    - Drawings of People (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Drawings of Dinosaurs / Monsters (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Drawings of Various Subjects (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Typeset Pages (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Source Artwork Related to Conceptual Ideas (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Un-mounted Posters, Covers, Photo, and Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Mounted DPN Covers (#4, 6, 7, 8,9) (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Mounted Drawings: Panels of Captain Condom, Other Mounted Art (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Mounted Drawings: Modes of Transportation (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Objects, undated, 1990; Series 6; 1 box
  This series contains ephemera from Diseased Pariah News and other organizations.
  - 9 "T Cell 100 (One Hundred) or Less" buttons, undated (Box-folder 6)
  - 6 "Kiss Me! I'm a Diseased Pariah" buttons, undated (Box-folder 6)
  - 2 "Porn Potato likes that!" buttons designed by Beowulf Thorne, 1990 (Box-folder 6)
  - 21 miscellaneous buttons, undated (Box-folder 6)
  - 1 Stanford AIDS Education Project's Fourth Annual Great Condom Rating Contest pamphlet with condoms, 1990 (Box-folder 6)
  - 1 "Kiss Me! I'm a Diseased Pariah" t-shirt, undated (Box-folder 6)
  - 1 Diseased Pariah News t-shirt, 1990 (Box-folder 6)
  - 1 Captain Condom Fan Club t-shirt, undated (Box-folder 6)